Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 5 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 December-1780 December Mss.B.F85inventory05
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1779.]; Diss. 3p.; -------, ------
    Commerce between Switzerland and the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778.]; Mem. 2p.; -------, ------
    A project for raising a regiment to invade England, Ireland and Scotland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779?]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; -------, ------
    Sending Franklin letters which he has just received for him from Miss Shipley.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 c Nov. 8]; A.L. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Departure of the courier of the Ambassador the following day; desires his translation of Franklin's letter together with the letter of M. de Vergennes and the Commission of Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 1; A.L.S. 4p.; Bilon, Louis Pierre. Lyons
    Wishes to go to America; remorse from a dishonorable action; will guard the secret of his real name until he receives Franklin's answer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 1; L in 3d P. 1p.; Beaumarchais, Pierre-Augustin Caron de. Paris
    In reference to fifty-six bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Dehez, Bernard. St. Sebastian
    Trouble brought upon him and the Commandant-General by the behavior of Capt. Conyngham, who obtained the release of four sailors and an officer, prisoners of war, on the understanding that he would make good any charges, should the Court at Madrid disapprove of their release; this promise he failed to keep.
  - to [George Washington ?], 1780 January 1; A.L.S. 8p.; Lixaute, Félix. Marmande
    Sends a poem, "The Complaint of the King of England," in which he eulogizes France and Franklin and vilifies England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Ducis, —, (veuve Morin). Paris
    Concerning a large order received from le Comte de Montfort to supply the hussrs at Philadelphia with various articles of clothing; in case the Count should be killed or the vessel taken, desires Franklin to keep the account of the articles, after he has seen them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Arrival of the "Serapis," "Pallas," and "Countess of Scarborough," with the brigantine, "Vengeance"; no mention made of Capt. Jones; imagines he proceeded through the Channel with the "Alliance."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 3; A.L.S. 4p.; Besson, George Leopold. Montbeillard
    None of his former requests for assistance have been answered.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 3; A.L.S. 4p.; Hartley, David. London
    Thinks the proposition for peace in May and June did some good, although opposed by the Ministry. Is strongly in favor of proposing a ten years' truce to America; part France would play in such an offer; objects to demanding the removal of troops as a preliminary measure; difficulties which confront the peace-maker; would take a bare-foot pilgrimage to Mecca to be assured of safe grounds to act upon; peace negotiations reported to be the object of Mr. Adams's mission; urges Franklin to be ever watchful for this great result.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Coder, Henry
    Has promised that Franklin would write to M. le Comte de Broglie, recommending M. Lair De Lamotte, M. Dubourg's nephew, for the position of Secretary.
    [Enclosed is a letter of introduction (1 p.), unsigned.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 3 [1781 ic. Jan. 3]; A.L.S. 2p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Col. [Patrick] Ferguson's defeat has frustrated, in a great measure, the enemy's designs against Virginia, but it is feared they will winter in Portsmouth.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Smith, William. St. Malo
    Born in Baltimore; shipped as officer in the first cruise of the "Bon Homme Richard"; was wounded and left, at his own expense, at l'Orient; desires a sufficient sum to enable him to redeem his trunk and clothes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 4; L.S. 2p.; Veuve Dque Morel and fils. Dunkirk
    Arrival of a portion of Commodore Jone's fleet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Woodmason, James. London
    Has shipped the paper; M. Beaumarchais's agent, M. Le Tailleir, returns to England in three weeks and will take charge to any letters; he has purchased Baskerville type for Voltaire's works. Superiority of English over foreign papers. Talk concerning peace very confident.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Lamarque, Fabre and Co. Paris
    Sending a bill of exchange payable at sight; good wishes for the success of the American cause.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 5; A.L.S. 1p.; de Peliepore, Abbé de la Fitte. Paris
    Sends a packet of letters for M. Plombard, the French Consul at Charleston; is very uneasy concerning his brother, the Chevalier de la Fitte.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Hartley, David. London
    Discusses the question of a ten years' truce in all its aspects; his reasons for treating with the present Ministry; rumor of Sir H. Clinton having been instructed to treat with America; if this is true, desires to know what terms he offered; Spanish papers report that the British Ministry, while openly avowing hopes of reconciliation, were bribing France to abandon America. Conjectures as to the object of Mr. [John] Adams's mission to Europe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Enclosing copies of the new protestations by certain Dutch towns against the Resolution in the States-General of Nov. 19th. [In French 5 p.] Departure of Capt. Jones and the squadron. His quarrel with the Grand Facteur; accused by him of having blackened the character of M. G[ran]d in Franklin's eyes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Sparre, [J.] de. Strasbourg
    Has written several letters to Franklin, offering to go to Philadelphia and establish a Military School there; expects his expenses to be defrayed; offers made by the British.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Bassemaison, Boullet. St. Malo
    Enclosing a letter from Mr. [William] Smith (XVII, 10, see p. 203) to whom he rendered some service; hopes Franklin will interest himself in Smith's case.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 6; A.L.S. 2p.; White, James. Haarlem
    Wrote two months before respecting his method for coloring cotton, wool and yarn, an art for which England, France and Spain offered £1,000 each; prefers to sail for America carrying his secret with him rather than obtain the premium from any one of these Kingdoms; on account of his losses in England and his long stay in Holland, is unable to carry out this plan without Franklin's assistance; should this fail, will be obliged, sorely against his will, to apply to Sir Joseph Yorke.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Taylor, Cradock. Aix
    Since the exchange of the English prisoners, as he refused to be classed in that category, his allowance has been stopped and he has subsisted solely on Franklin's small donation; cannot sail for Martinique until the end of the month, and not then, unless Franklin advances him a small sum for the discharge of his debts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Lloyd, Richard Bennett. London
    Has decided to sail for America in the spring; the best and safest way of conveying his family across the Atlantic. Before leaving Europe, would like to tell Franklin something of interest which he cannot trust to paper.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Corail de Sainte-Foy, François de. Toulouse
    At the request of two brave officers in the service of the Emperor, sends Franklin the two enclosed packets.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 8; A.L.S. 3p.; von Doppelmair, Capt. Anspach
    Was in the Prussian service. Offers his services to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 8; A.L.S. 3p.; von Weckherlein, Major Gottlieb Christian. Anspach
    Refers to Lieut-General von Saldern, under whom he served. Offers his services to the American cause.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David. London
    Surprised at not hearing from Franklin for two months, relative to the Cartel; sends copy of letter from the Board of Sick and Hurt, dated November 15th, 1779. [See XVI, 109.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Gérard. L'Orient
    Arrival in port of the "Black Prince", after being hotly pursued by two English frigates; since the 21st of December, she made five prizes and four ransoms; the prisoners, numbering forty-eight, will be landed and cared for.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Interview with M. de Montbarrey, on the subject of forwarding military supplies for the American Army.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 410).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 9; L.S. 5p.; Digges, Thomas. London
    Giving fictitious names under cover of which their correspondence can be safely forwarded. Gives memoranda concerning maps of Great Britain and Ireland, bought by order of William Temple Franklin and lately shipped via Amsterdam. Also enclose bill for books.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. Paris
    Extracts from the letter of John P. Jones to Dr. Franklin, dated at the Texel, October 3d, 1779; begs Franklin to certify that they are a true copy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Mante, Thomas. Paris
    Begs Franklin to assist him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Concerning his efforts to obtain military supplies for the American army.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 411).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Complaints against England's treatment of Dutch ships. The "Serapis," "Scarborough," "Pallas" and "Vengeance" said to be safe at Dunkirk; whereabouts of the "Alliance." M. de Neufville's accounts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 Before June 10] [1780 On or After Aug 31]; A.L.S. 7p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Safe arrival of the squadron under Commodore Jones; the settlement of their expenses. Terms of a certain loan. Question of passports for some of their friends who intend to enrage in the American business. Had the pleasure of seeing Baron [de] Wülffen, Aide-de-camp to the great Gen. Washington. Rumor of the French and Spanish fleets having joined forces. Promising to forward Franklin a portrait of Gen. Washington, designed for him, by some one whose name, at present, is a secret. Report from America of the taking of St. Lucia, Barbadoes and Antigua.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 12; L.S. 3p.; John Diot and Co. Morlaix
    Forwarding a copy of the journal of the "Black Princess"; arrival of two of her prizes, and one belonging to the "Black Prince"; begs for their speedy condemnation. Uneasy at hearing no tidings of the "Black Prince."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Gérard. L'Orient
    Encloses list of prisoners taken by the "Black Prince," which sailed on the 11th for Brest, where she expected to find her prizes awaiting her; report received of the arrival of only one.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Marazzani, —, comte de. Paris
    Desires to pay his respects to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 13.; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Veillard, Geneviève-Elisabeth Belamy (Louis-Guillaume's wife). Dreux
    Thanking him for the prettiest little desk in the world; its only fault is that it failed to contain a letter saying that he still loved her a little; hopes in a month to be again at Passy where she may once more embrace him; messages from her father and mother; if the desk is his grandson's choice, considers him a young man of extraordinary good taste.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. Paris
    Concerning his capture of the two Swedish ships; without the ship's papers, can say no more. Question of the accusations brought against him and their utter falsity; expected to have his conduct justified ere this.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1780 January 14; A.L.S. Fra[nci]s Hopkinson. 1p.; The Treasurer of Loans. Philadelphia
    Notification of bills of exchange furnished to the States of RhodeIsland and New York.
    (In triplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Mary,------
    Has been granted a passage, by the Minister of Marine, upon the first vessel sailing for North America; hears that the Continental frigate, the "Committee," sails from Nantes in a few days; desires a letter of recommendation to Franklin's Agent in Nantes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Has forwarded particulars of the first fine success of the "Black Prince" and "Princess." Has purchased that day, for the brave Capt. Luke Ryan, the fine large cutter lately commanded by Capt. Royer, which is to be called the "Fearnot"; asks for an American Commission for the Captain. Sixty-six prisoners taken by the above-mentioned ships, are landed and at Franklin's disposal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Begs that the enclosed letter may be forwarded.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 16; A.L.S. 4p.; Jones, Paul Jno. "The Alliance."
    His safe passage through the Channel, in spite of the enemy's attempts to cut off his retreat; would have given them cause for fresh alarm, had not his sails and rigging been in such a bad condition; description of a brigantine from Liverpool, sailing under Dutch colors, which he took and sent to America; extremely vexatious to see the enemy carrying on half their trade under neutral colors; expects to proceed towards his destined port in France; reasons why he thinks the Court cannot refuse to fit out his ship upon her arrival.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Titot, ------. Colmar
    His position of Governor of the Royal Military School at Colmar; his long-cherished desire to serve in the American army; is twenty-five years old. Wishes to know what steps he must take to carry out his plan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Asking for a letter of introduction for his wife's grandfather, John Aitcheson, from M. d'Estaing to the Governor or to some principal person in the Island of Grenada.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Begging for the release of eight Irish prisoners, who have sworn allegiance to the United States, and who have been promised berths in the crew of the "Fearnot"; much in want of such good sailors.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Dixon, John. Williamsburg
    Encloses letter for his father in Yorkshire; in case his son-in-law [step-son] William Royal is sent to America via France, asks Franklin to recommend him to the care of some good Captain coming to Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Carlo, Conte de Zizendorp. Trieste
    Recommending his friend, Dominique François Belletti.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Gourlade and Moylan. L'Orient
    The arrival of the "Black Prince" at l'Orient some days before; during eighteen days' cruise in the English Channel, she made several captures and deposited forty-eight prisoners; desires to know if they are to be regarded as the property of the United States, in which case, they must be distinguished from the prisoners of France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Joseph Gardoqui and Sons. Bilbao
    Enclosing letters for the Hon. John Adams, whose agreeable company they have been enjoying and who sets out for Paris on the 20th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Baudot, -----. Semur
    One of his relatives, a young officer, desires to serve in the American army; requests information as to the expense of the voyage and the articles needed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780?] January 20; A.L. 3p.; Brillon, Mme
    Refers to the taking of St. Eustace and the consternation caused by the news in the English Colony at Nice. Her house is next to that of Lady Rivers (formerly Mrs. Pitt). Tells of a concert given at the latter's house at which Mme. Brillon played the "Insurgent's March" composed by herself. Account of a conversation with Lord Cholmondeley on the same occasion. He is desirous to meet Franklin and promises to take tea at Mme. Brillon's house at Passy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 20; A.L.S. 1p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    They desire Franklin's advice in regard to the payment of a draft.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Auzoüer, ----, marquis d'
    Begs for news of Mrs. Carroll, a relative of his wife, and wishes to know if Mr. Carroll will be Franklin's successor, in the event of his quitting France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 21 [1781 ie Jan. 21]; A.L.S. 1p. ;1p.; Chaumont, Le Ray de
    In receipt of news from America; his interest in his own country and in Franklin's should be a close bond of union between them.
    Agreement attached relative to the vessel, the "Marquis de la Fayette."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Rayber, ---- chevalier de
    Claims that he was promised the position of Captain of Marines, by Commodore Guillin [Gillon], who told him to await at Nantes the orders he would send by Capt. [William] Robeson; has heard nothing since; his letters unanswered and he himself reduced to the last degree of poverty and misery; begs for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Robeson, William. Nantes
    Promised, by Mr. Williams, a passage to America on board the "Marquis de la Fayette"; unable to wait longer for the departure of this vessel; asks for a passage on one of the French frigates shortly to sail from Brest to Rhode Island; will be glad to carry any despatches and would be obliged for an introduction to Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Enclosing a letter [1 p.] from the Baron de la Houze relative to the two prizes seized at Bergen and restored to the English. Anxious for tidings of Paul Jones, also for news of the ship "Confederacy," carrying Messrs. [John] Jay and [William] Carmichael.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 25; L.S. 2p.; Sayn et Wittgenstein, Jean-Louis, comte de. Wittgenstein
    Since 1776, le Sieur Lutterloh has owed him and his subjects a large sum of money; believes him, at present, to be serving with distinction in Washington's army; thinks he will be willing to pay his debts if he has the means; begs for Franklin's mediation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Dowlin, Patrick. "Black Prince," Brest
    Has taken three valuable prizes, four ransoms, and put forty-three captives into the prison at l'Orient; his consort; the "Black Princess," boasts four prizes, will send copy of journal and the names of the prisoners; hopes shortly to be ready to join the "Black Princess" at the Ile of Ross.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Having received no answer to his letter of Nov. 23rd, presumes it miscarried; miserable condition of the American prisoners, who number 1,100; does not understand why nothing has been done to forward the exchange as the English Board of Sick and Hurt are most anxious to do their part; another passport needed, as two vessels will not be sufficient.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Ryan, Luke. Dunkirk
    His health perfectly restored; waits with impatience the commission for his ship the "Fearnot"; his refusal of offers made by the French will only serve under the American flag; refuses to expose himself to the insults of French officers. His scheme for the Bristol fair of March, will, he hopes, deprive the fair of some linen and other cargoes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Departure of Mr. Adams from Bayonne. His reasons for thinking the "Confederacy" has foundered; bewails the difficulty and uncertainty of correspondence with the United States; suggests the benefits of having monthly packet boats; in daily expectation of valuable arrivals from America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 January 31; A.L.S. 2p.; John Diot and Co. Morlaix
    Referring Franklin to their letter of the 12th inst.; enclosing a copy of the journal of the "Black Prince"; their anxiety lest two of the prizes taken by the "Princess" have been retaken or lost; think both privateers will be ready for sea again in a few days; need of the prizes being speedily judged and condemned, on account of the great demand for provisions in the French navy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 Jan. 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Fleury, Lieut.-Col. François Louis Teisseidre de. Paris
    Asking to have his medal [ordered by the Congress] struck by the following week, as the King desires to see it; suggestions for the design.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 Dec. 25]; A.L.S. 2p.; Woodmason, James. London
    Promising to send the twelve reams of paper as soon as it has been marbled.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 February 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Irritation of a certain great person against the English owing to their treatment of the Dutch ships; his expressed intention to propose a new resolution in favor of unlimited convoys, annulling all subsequent bills opposed to this measure. Information concerning the Baron de la H[ouze].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 February 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Taylor, John. Bath
    His claim, through Ralph Fretwell, to a considerable tract of land in Chester County, Pa.; has the original warrant; desires advice as to how to proceed in the matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779] February 2; L. 1p.; Raynal, Abbé. Paris
    Inviting Dr. Franklin and Mr. John Adams to tea.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 February 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Servieres, —. Hesdin
    Has been authorized by M. Necker to write a treatise on the comparative cultivation of tobacco; among other works, has need of one on the cultivation of tobacco in Virginia published in England a few years before; if it is in Franklin's possession, begs him to forward it with any other treatises on the subject he may be able to procure; relies on M. Necker and the Chevalier de Keralio to speak for him in this matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 February 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    The unanimous resolution of the Holland Assembly for unlimited convoys. Not yet the right moment to propose a treaty to Holland. Account of a M. G(u)illon at Amsterdam, who passes as a United States Admiral and has the confidence of M. Van Berkel and other distinguished persons; suspects some intrigue like that of Mr. W[illam] L[ee] or Mr. Izard.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 February 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Scott, George. Paris
    Will send his servant for an answer to the question enclosed on a separate paper herein.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 February 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Montago, Mourete, marquise de. Beaucaire
    Writes on behalf of Pierre Colomb, who desires to enter the service of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 February 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Taylor, Cradock. Aix
    Begs for a sufficient sum to enable him to return to his own country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 February 8; A.L.S.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Rumor that Capt. Jones is cruizing off the coast of Ireland. Baron de la H[ouze] not to be trusted. Anxious concerning the fate of the "Confederacy."